Guide to the Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, 1841-1992, bulk 1845-1849, 1854-1857, and 1864-1892
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Material About or Relating to Whitman Series, 1842-1947 and undated (bulk post-1880)
  - Books And Pamphlets About Or Relating To Whitman Subseries, 1842-1947 (bulk 1880-1930).
    - Elliot, Charles N. Walt Whitman as Man, Poet and Friend. Boston, 1915., (2 copies); Former call number: Trent IV
    - Erskine, John. The Start of the Road. New York, 1938., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Fausset, Hugh I'Anson. Walt Whitman: Poet of Democracy. New Haven, 1942., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Figuiere, Eugene. Walt Whitman (Poete Americain). Les Anthologies du Xxe siecle Series. Paris, 1928., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Fowler, O. S. Fowler's Practical Phrenology. Bound with Phrenology Proved, Illustrated, and Applied. New York, 1849., Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________. Phrenology and Physiology Explained and Applied to Matrimony... to the Cultivation of Memory... to Temperance; and to the Evils of Tight-Lacing. New York, 1842.
    - __________, L. N. Fowler, and Samuel Kirkham. Phrenology Proved, Illustrated, and Applied. Bound with Fowler's Practical Phrenology. New York, 1849.
    - Garcia Lorca, Federico. Poems. Translated by Stephen Spender and J. L. Gli, edited by and introduction by R. M. Nadal. New York and Toronto, 1939., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Garland, Hamlin. Roadside Meetings. New York, 1930., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Gilchrist, Herbert Harlakenden, editor. Introduction by William Michael Rossetti. Anne Gilchrist: Her Life and Writings. Second edition. London, 1887., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Gould, Elizabeth Porter. Anne Gilchrist and Walt Whitman. Philadelphia, 1900., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Grebanier, Francis, writing as Francis Winwar. American Giant: Walt Whitman and His Times. New York and London, 1941., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Hartley, L. Conrad. The Spirit of Walt Whitman. Manchester (Lancs.), 1908., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Hartmann, C. Sadakichi. Conversations with Walt Whitman. New York, 1895., Former call number: Pam 12mo H333 C
    - Heartman, Charles F. The Untimeliness of the Walt Whitman Exhibition at the New York Public Library. New York, 1925., Former call number: Pam 12mo H436 U
    - Higginson, Thomas Wentworth. Contemporaries. Boston and New York, 1899., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Holloway, Emory. Whitman: An Interpretation in Narrative. New York and London, 1926., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Hubbard, Elbert. Walt Whitman. Little Journeys to the Homes of American Authors Series, vol. 11, no. 6. New York and London, 1896., Former call number: Pam 12mo H845 W
    - Huneker, James Gibbons. Ivory Apes and Peacocks. New York, 1915., Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________. Letters of James Gibbons Huneker. Edited by Josephine Huneker. New York, 1922.
    - Ingersoll, Robert G. House of Death: Being Funeral Orations and Addresses. London, 1897., Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________. Liberty in Literature: Testimonial to Walt Whitman. New York, 1890.
    - Irwin, Mabel McCoy. Whitman: The Poet-Liberator of Woman. New York, 1905., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Johnson, Lorenzo D. Memoria Technica: or, The Art of Abbreviating Those Studies Which Give the Greatest Labor to the Memory. Second edition. Boston, 1847., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Johnston, John. Diary Notes of a Visit to Walt Whitman and Some of His Friends, in 1890. Manchester and London, 1898., Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________. Notes of a Visit to Walt Whitman, Etc., in July, 1890. Bolton, 1890.
    - __________ and J. W. Wallace. Visits to Walt Whitman in 1890-1891. London, 1917.
    - Karsner, David. Horace Traubel: His Life and Work. New York, 1919., Former call number: Trent IV
    - "Katinka." Abbie Nott and Other Knots. Philadelphia, 1856., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Keller, Elizabeth Leavitt. Walt Whitman in Mickle Street. New York, 1921., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Kennedy, William Sloane. The Fight of a Book for the World: A Companion Volume to Leaves of Grass. Winter Park (Fla.), 1926., Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________. Reminiscences of Walt Whitman with Extracts from his Letters and Remarks on his Writings. London, 1896., (2 copies)
    - Knortz, Karl. Walt Whitman. New York, 1886., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Kouwenhoven, John A. Adventures of America, 1857- 1900: A Pictorial Record from Harper's Weekly. New York and London, 1938., Former call number: III-11
    - Legler, Henry Eduard. Walt Whitman: Yesterday and Today. Chicago, 1916., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Lowell, Amy. Poetry and Poets. Boston and New York, 1930., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Masters, Edgar Lee. Whitman. New York, 1937., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Mathews, Godfrey W. Walt Whitman. Liverpool, 1921., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Matthiessen, F. O. American Renaissance: Art and Expression in the Age of Emerson and Whitman. London, Toronto, and New York, 1941., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Maynard, Mila Tupper. Walt Whitman: The Poet of the Wider Selfhood. Chicago, 1903., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Mercer, Dorothy Frederica. "Leaves of Grass and the Bhagavad Gita: A Comparative Study." Typescript. Ph.D. dissertation. University of California, 1933., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Mordell, Albert. Notorious Literary Attacks. New York, 1926., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Mumford, Lewis. The Golden Day: A Study in American Experience and Culture. New York, 1926., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Newton, A. Edward. A Magnificent Farce, and Other Diversions of a Book-Collector. Boston, 1921., Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________. A Magnificent Farce... Large paper edition. Boston, 1921.
    - Norton, Charles Eliot. A Leaf of Grass from Shady Hill. Cambridge (Mass.), 1928., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Noyes, Carleton. An Approach to Walt Whitman. Boston and New York, 1910., Former call number: Trent IV
    - O'Connor, William D. Harrington: A Story of True Love. Boston, 1860., Former call number: IV O18 H
    - Overton, Grant. The Answerer. New York, 1921., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Parrington, Vernon Louis. Main Currents in American Thought: An Interpretation of American Literature from the Beginnings to 1920. New York, 1930, Former call number: Trent IV
    - Perry, Bliss. Walt Whitman: His Life and Work. Boston and New York, 1906., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Platt, Isaac Hull. Walt Whitman. Beacon Biographies of Eminent Americans Series. Boston, 1907., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Pond, Major J. B. Eccentricities of Genius: Memories of Famous Men and Women of the Platform and Stage. New York, 1900., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Powys, John Cowper. Visions and Revisions: A Book of Literary Devotions. New York and London, 1915., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Riethmueller, Richard. Walt Whitman and the Germans: A Study. Philadelphia, 1906., Former call number: Pam q R563 W
    - Rivers, W. C. Walt Whitman's Anomaly. London, 1913., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Rogers, Cameron. The Magnificent Idler: The Story of Walt Whitman. Garden City (NY), 1926., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Rossetti, William Michael. Letters of William Michael Rossetti concerning Whitman, Blake, and Shelley, to Anne Gilchrist and Her Son Herbert Gilchrist. Edited by Clarence Gohdes and Paull Franklin Baum. Durham (NC), 1934., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Sanborn, Kate. The Vanity and Insanity of Genius. New York, 1886., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Saunders, Henry S., editor. Parodies on Walt Whitman. New York, 1923., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Sawyer, Roland D. Walt Whitman: The Prophet-Poet. Boston, 1913., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Shephard, Esther. Walt Whitman's Prose. New York, 1938., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Smith, Logan Pearsall. Unforgotten Years. London, 1938., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Smith, William. A Yorkshireman's Trip to the United States and Canada. London, 1892., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Stevenson, Robert Louis. The Essay on Walt Whitman. East Aurora (NY), 1900., (2 copies); Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________. Familiar Studies of Men and Books. London, 1882.
    - __________. Familiar Studies... London, 1888.
    - Swinburne, Algernon Charles. Songs Before Sunrise. Boston, 1871., Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________. Under the Microscope. London, 1872.
    - Symonds, John Addington. A Problem in Modern Ethics: Being an Inquiry into the Phenomenon of Sexual Inversion. London, 1896., Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________. Walt Whitman: A Study. London, 1893., (2 copies)
    - Thomson, James. Walt Whitman: The Man and the Poet. London, 1910., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Traubel, Horace L., editor. At the Graveside of Walt Whitman: Harleigh, Camden, New Jersey, March 30th. [No place of publication identified in Frey], 1892., Former call number: Trent IV
    - __________, editor. Camden's Compliment to Walt Whitman, May 31, 1889. Philadelphia, 1889.
    - __________. With Walt Whitman in Camden. 3 vols. New York, 1914-1915.
    - Triggs, Oscar L. Browning And Whitman: A Study in Democracy. London and New York, 1893., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Trowbridge, John Townsend. My Own Story: With Recollections of Noted Persons. First edition. Boston and New York, 1903., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Wharton, Edith. Old New York: The Spark (The 'Sixties). New York and London, 1924., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Wilson, Francis. Francis Wilson's Life of Himself. Boston and New York, 1924., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Wilson, Jane Bliss. Index of the Whitman Clippings. Master's thesis, 1947., Former call number: Trent IV
    - Winwar, Francis, pseudonym [See Grebanier, Francis]
    - Wright, Frank Lloyd. An Autobiography. New York, 1943., Former call number: Trent IV
- Portraits Series, 1854-1891 and undated
  Contains painted portraits, sketches, engravings, etchings, and photographs of Whitman and other subjects.
  - Portraits of Walt Whitman Subseries, 1854-1891 and undated
    Where artist and date of a portrait are known, they are included below. Reproductions of most of the portraits are included in Whitman Portraits, edited by Henry S. Saunders, call number Trent IV S257 Wh. Entries for those portraits appearing in Whitman Portraits include Saunders' catalog number. Saunders' book catalogues portraits according to Whitman's age, thus lower-numbered items generally refer to images of a younger Whitman. Listed alphabetically by artist or photographer. See also photographs in the Miscellany Series.
    - Anonymous
      - Photograph, circa 1854 (Saunders 5), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
      - Photograph, 1869; Whitman with Peter Doyle (Saunders 29)
      - Photograph, 1869; Whitman with Peter Doyle (Saunders 30)
      - Photograph, 1869 (Saunders 96), Former call number: III-5 (Box III-5)
      - Photograph, Brooklyn, 1871 (Saunders 35), Former call number: IV-B972 N or III-6A
      - Photograph, 1872 (Saunders 38), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
      - Photograph, 1873 (Saunders 42)
      - Photograph with Kitty and Harold Johnston, 1879 (Saunders 68)
      - Photograph, 1888 (Saunders 100)
      - Oil painting, 1889 (Saunders 105)
      - Portrait reproduced in The Review of Reviews, Vol. III, no. 14: 1891, Feb., p. 163, Former call number: V, Trent Pam Case
      - Photograph, undated (Saunders 37.1), Former call number: I-3 (Box I-3)
      - Photograph, Gribaydoff, undated (Saunders 37.1a), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
      - Photograph, tinted, undated (Saunders 70)
      - Photograph, undated (Saunders 101), Former call number: II-7A 149 (Box II-7A 149)
      - Photograph of bust by Sidney Morse, undated (Saunders 301), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
      - Whitman portrait (Blatas), undated
      - Reproduction of Photograph, 1890 (Saunders 112), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Brady, Mathew
      - Photograph, Washington, 1869 (Saunders 24), Former call number: II-9 or III-6B (Box II-9 or III-6B)
        II-9: framed, with a postcard to Edward Carpenter, cf. Correspondence From or By Whitman Subseries; III-6A: photograph only.
      - Photograph (Saunders 45), undated, Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Coughlin, Jack
      - Etching, undated, Former call number: Trent Folio I-1
    - Cox, George C.
      - Photograph (Saunders 92), 1887, Sept., Former call number: MS q 191 (Volume MS q 191)
      - Photograph (Saunders 92), 1887, Sept., Former call number: II-7C 201 (Box II-7C 201)
      - Photograph (Saunders 95), 1887, Sept., Former call number: III-6B 144a (Box III-6B 144a)
    - Edy Brothers, London, Ont.
      - 1880 Sept. 22 (Saunders 75), Former call number: II-6B 142a (Box II-6B 142a)
    - Gardner
      - Photograph, Washington 1863 (Saunders 21), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Gilchrist, Herbert
      - Photo-intaglio from a drawing, undated; (Saunders 81.1), (2 copies); Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Gutekunst, F.
      - Photograph (reproduction), 1880; (Saunders 80), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Jaeckel, Willi
      - Lithograph, undated (Saunders 37), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Johnson, T.
      - Etching, 1891 (Saunders 95a), Former call number: III-6B (Box III-6B)
    - Johnston, Dr. John
      - Photograph, Whitman with Warren Fritzinger, 1890, July (Saunders 108), Former call number: MS q 194 (Volume MS q 194)
      - Photograph, With Warry, 1890 (Saunders 109), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
      - Photograph, Whitman, solus, 1890 (Saunders 110), Former call number: MS q 203 (Volume MS q 203)
    - Kennedy, Bartlett F.
      - Photograph, Boston, The Pompous Photo, undated (Saunders 85), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Kotz, E. Whittlesey
      - Charcoal sketch, 1887, 11 Feb. (Saunders 95e), Former call number: III-6B (Box III-6B)
    - Kruell, G.
      - Woodcut (Saunders 37.1b), Former call number: II-7C (Box II-7C)
    - Kurtz, W.
      - Photograph, Whitman with Harry and Kitty Johnston, 1879 (Saunders 68), Former call number: MS q 195 (Volume MS q 195)
    - Linton, W. J.
      - Woodcut (reproduction), 1871 (Saunders 44a), Former call number: II-4, II-7B, III-6A (Box II-4, II-7B, III-6A)
        III-6A copy with title page of 1876 "Author's Edition" of Leaves of Grass.
    - Pearsall, Frank, Former call number: II-9 or III-6A (Box II-9 or III-6A)
      - Photograph, undated (Saunders 31)
        Copy in II-9 included with letter to William Sloane Kennedy, 1 Apr. 1890, a ticket to Whitman's lecture on Lincoln at Madison Square Theater 14 Apr. 1887, and a clipping from the Philadelphia Press 16 Apr. 1887 describing the lecture. Cf. Correspondence From or By Whitman Subseries.
      - Photograph, undated (Saunders 32), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Pearsall, G. F. E.
      - Photograph, 1872 (Saunders 36), Former call number: MS 19 (Volume MS 19)
        Cf. Manuscript Poems Subseries: Poems not Appearing in Leaves of Grass.
      - Photograph, 1872 (Saunders 36), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
        Cf. Manuscript Poems Subseries: Notes for Poems.
    - Phillips and Taylor
      - Photograph, 1883 (Saunders 48), Former call number: MS q 205 (Volume MS q 205)
    - Potter and Co., Philadelphia
      - Photograph, 1882 (Saunders 83), Former call number: MS q 140 (Volume MS q 140)
    - Sarony
      - Photograph, 1879 (Saunders 57), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Schnelle, William G.
      - Three-colored cut, undated (Saunders 87.1), (2 copies); Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Schoff
      - Steel engraving, circa 1863 (Saunders 11a), (2 copies); Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - attrib. Smith, William Russell
      - Oil portrait, undated, Former call number: Trent West Wall
    - Waters, G. W.
      - Sketch (reprod.), 1877 (Saunders 52), Former call number: II-6A 138 (Box II-6A 138)
    - Woolf, S. J.
      - Lithograph, ca. 1940, Former call number: III-6B (Box III-6B)
  - Portraits of Others Subseries, 1862 and undated
    This largely undated subseries consists of renderings of some of Whitman's friends and his brother George. Listed alphabetically by name of subject of image.
    - Burroughs, John, Former call number: IV-B972N
      - Anon.; engraving, undated
    - Farwell, Reuben, Former call number: III-6B (Box III-6B)
      - Anon.; pencil drawing, undated
    - Hay, John, Former call number: Storage
      - Anon.; photograph, undated
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, Former call number: II display
      - Anon.; photograph, undated
        Includes a letter by Holmes of 18 Feb. 1890; Cf. Correspondence To or About Whitman Subseries.
    - Sand, George, Former call number: III-6B (Box III-6B)
      - E. Baumann; pencil drawing, undated
    - Whitman, Hannah, Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
      - Anon.; photograph, undated
    - Whitman, George W., Former call number: III-5B (Box III-5B)
      - Anon.; hand-colored tintype, 1862 [?]
- Miscellany Series, 1855-1992 and undated
  Series contains literary and personal ephemera, as well as some material relating to the Whitman fund set up in England in the 1880s. Also included are memorabilia from Whitman's seventieth birthday banquet and a scrapbook containing pictures and clippings from newspapers and periodicals published in the years following Whitman's death. Research files on Whitman collected by Bliss Perry and Walter C. Rivers may also be found here. A file of correspondence addressed to the latter on the subject of Whitman's homosexuality includes transcriptions of letters from Perry and other contemporary Whitman scholars. Also included are several photographs of Whitman's house and additional portraits from Whitman Portraits, edited by Henry S. Saunders, call number Trent IV S257 Wh. Listed alphabetically by descriptive title.
  - Facsimile manuscripts and original ephemera from Charles E. Feinberg, Former call number: M1 (Box M1)
  - Whitman's trunk label (photograph), Former call number: M1 (Box M1)
  - Correspondence and description of the autographed manuscript of Leaves of Grass, 1939, Former call number: M1 (Box M1)
  - Alboni, Marietta, La Mia Estensione, undated, Former call number: III-9C (Box III-9C)
  - The Asian Student, 1968 Apr. 6, Former call number: I-7 (Box I-7)
  - Bliss Perry Whitman Collection
    Research notebooks on Whitman collected by Bliss Perry. Vols. I and II contain transcribed correspondence, the bulk of which are addressed to William D. O'Connor and his family. Vols. IV and V contain various research files compiled by Perry.
    - Vols. I and II, Former call number: II-8A (Box II-8A)
    - Vols. IV and V, Former call number: II-8B (Box II-8B)
  - Copies of letters addressed to Walter C. Rivers on the subject of Walt Whitman's homosexuality, 1913-1916, Former call number: III-9C (Box III-9C)
  - Daily Collegian, 1963 Feb. 28, Former call number: I-7 (Box I-7)
  - Early Roman History photocopy, undated, Former call number: III-9C (Box III-9C)
  - English Subscribers, undated, Former call number: III-8A or III-8C (Box III-8A or III-8C)
    Leaflet containing a letter by Whitman and a list of English subscribers to the Whitman fund (2 copies).
  - Garrett, Florence. To Whitman, undated, Former call number: III-9C (Box III-9C)
    Copy of poem donated by the author.
  - Halcyon Days, 1977 Dec. 8
    Printed copy of poem on Christmas card.
  - Leaves of Grass wrappers, 1855, Former call number: III-8A (Box III-8A)
    Three sets of original wrappers for the first edition of Leaves of Grass.
  - National State Bank of Camden check signed by Whitman, 1875 March 27, Former call number: III-9C (Box III-9C)
  - New York Herald, 1865 April 15, Former call number: III-6B (Box III-6B)
    Front page reporting the assassination of Abraham Lincoln.
  - Personal note, 1876, Former call number: III-8A (Box III-8A)
    Proof as issued.
  - Photographs
    - Envelope of photos laid in Saunders, Henry S. Whitman Portraits, undated, Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
    - Portraits from Life, undated
    - Prints used to illustrate Frey, Ellen, Catalogue of the Whitman Collection, undated
    - Whitman's birthplace, undated
  - Photostats of Whitman notebook, undated, Former call number: III-8A (Box III-8A)
  - Photostats of Whitman family papers from the Library of Congress, Former call number: III-9C (Box III-9C)
    In addition to photostats, correspondence between Josiah Trent and Library of Congress staff about holdings there are also housed in this location.
  - Piece of Walt Whitman's hair cut off by R. M. Bucke at Camden, 1886 July 20, Former call number: III-9C (Box III-9C)
  - Remembrance Copy, [1876?], Former call number: BT III-8
    First two printed pages of Memoranda During the War, 1875-1876,
  - Scrapbook of Whitman Correspondence and Clippings, 1892-1926, Former call number: I-8C (Box I-8C)
    Collected by William Sloane Kennedy.
  - Scrapbook of Whitman Clippings and Miscellany, undated, Former call number: I-8A (Box I-8A)
    Includes section on John Steinbeck in addition to Whitman material.
  - Scrapbook of Whitman Pictures and Clippings, 1892-1926, Former call number: I-8B (Box I-8B)
    Collected by William Schroeder.
  - Trent, Josiah C., notes and correspondence on Walt Whitman--A Case History, Former call number: III-9C (Box III-9C)
    Article by J. C. Trent, M.D. appeared in Surgery, Gynecology, and Obstetrics, 87: 113-121, July 1948
  - Untitled autograph manuscript, beginning "Feats of Civility..."; with 1944 Feb 4 letter by Alfred Goldsmith, Former call number: III-9C (Box III-9C)
    Letter from Goldsmith suggests Ralph Waldo Emerson as a possible author of the manuscript (previously may have been thought to have been by Whitman)
  - Walt Whitman on Abraham Lincoln, 1887 Apr. 14, Former call number: III-6B (Box III-6B)
    Card announcing Whitman's lecture on Lincoln at Madison Square Theater in New York. For ticket to and Philadelphia Press account ( 1887 Apr. 16) of this lecture, Cf. Correspondence From or By Whitman Subseries.
  - Walt Whitman Audio Materials, 1992, Former call number: I-9A (Box I-9A)
    Audiocassette and related program from a concert given at the University of Iowa.
    [Original audiocassette closed to use. Technical Services may need to have a use copy made before contents can be accessed. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this material.]
  - Walt Whitman. September 1885, 1885 Sept., Former call number: III-8A (Box III-8A)
    Leaflet announcing the formation of a subscription list in England for Whitman's benefit.
  - Walt Whitman's Buggy and Horse, 1885 Sept. 17
    Leaflet of receipts for horse and buggy.
  - Walt Whitman's Seventieth Birthday, 1889 May 31, Former call number: Trent V
    Menu and program for Whitman's seventieth birthday banquet. Includes a portrait.